- Let's talk about code
reviews for a second.
Let's push the boundary on
optimizing for correctness,
because without a measuring stick
how do we really know we're doing things
and making the best decisions?
I told you that everything
comes with a cost.
Nothing is free.
What is the cost for taking
for the benefit that we need?
How do we know this piece of code we wrote
is optimized for correctness first?
Here's my measuring stick.
As we start looking at code
and start talking about code,
this is gonna come up over
and over and over again.
I'm going to stress it.
And our number one priority
must always be integrity.
Integrity must be first.
In fact, Go puts integrity above all else.
It is built deep into the language.
Now here's another buzzword, integrity.
I mean, what does integrity mean?
What integrity means is
that we become serious
about writing code that is reliable.
Let me ask you a question.
Here's our cell phone, here it is.
If this cell phone stopped working,
I mean, just stopped working for an hour,
just an hour, across the United States,
how many people are gonna die?
It's a serious question.
The answer is definitely not zero.
Our lives depend on technology,
and the software we write,
whether you want to believe it or not,
is a part of that fabric that's
holding society together.
We can no longer not take
what we do seriously.
We don't need license for what we do.
We're not regulated, we make mistakes,
and it's, ah, no, no more.
We have to, we have to
take reliability seriously.
It starts with us.
We have to remember how serious
the software that we're writing is.
Now, for me, integrity
comes in two pieces,
a micro level and a macro level.
At the micro-level,
integrity is about every read,
every write, every memory
allocation that we perform
being accurate, consistent, and efficient.
I mean, think about this for a second.
Every line of code we write
really just does one
of these three things.
We either allocate memory,
we read memory, or we write memory.
Integrity is about making sure that all,
one of those three
operations are accurate, consistent,
and efficient, because when they're not,
we have an integrity issue,
we're corrupting data,
things have to shut down.
Think about what I just said.
We're corrupting data.
And that's the other part of this.
Everything we do, every problem we solve,
everything we think about
boils down to becoming a
data transformation problem.
We have some input, and
we produce some output.
Everything we do, every function we write,
every method we write
is a data transformation.
Everything.
So integrity also means that
every data transformation
that we have to perform, every
problem we have to solve,
must also be accurate,
consistent and efficient.
Now, at a macro level, how do we do this?
Well, there's two big things.
One, we have to write less code.
You know, NASA or, there've been studies.
There've been studies on
what the average developer
produces in bugs,
depending on the number of
lines of code they write.
It's staggering how
the average developer
produces so many bugs.
We have to write less code.
Less code means less bugs.
Error handling is also critical
to everything we do.
I want you to think about this.
There is a study that was done,
looking at several big software products.
Cassandra, MapReduce, Redis.
Technologies you probably know about.
They did this study of
48 critical failures.
And what did they discover?
They discovered that 92% of that 48,
92% could have been avoided,
if the error handling was taken seriously,
if the error handling became
part of their priority.
And this is a key.
Error handling cannot be an exception.
It must be part of the main code.
It is part of the code you're writing.
Go doesn't exception handling,
Go doesn't have that try-catch.
Go doesn't say, we'll deal
with errors over here.
No, if integrity matters,
then error handling is not an exception.
It's gotta be part of your main code.
I'm sorry if you feel that maybe
that's gonna be a little tedious for you.
But what's more important?
What's the cost trade-off?
A little tedi-ness in error handling
versus integrity, 92%?
I could tell you right now
that nothing ever can trump integrity.
No decision you make,
no decision you make
can ever have integrity be the cost.
And that means error handling
must be part of the main
code that you're writing.
Here is that study on the less code.
What the average developer does is produce
somewhere between 15 and 50
bugs per thousand lines of code,
which means that some
of the worst developers
who don't care about
integrity might be producing
a bug in almost every 20 lines of code.
Imagine that, every 20
lines of code you write,
whether you like it or not, is a bug.
How do we reduce bugs,
we gotta write less code.
That ties back into integrity.
Because when we write
more code than we need,
it results in ugly, large, and slow code.
Ugly leaves places for bugs
to hide, think about it.
More code, more places for bugs to be,
more places for bugs to hide,
because we need so many more tests
to get the code coverage
levels that we need,
it becomes almost impossible.
And if the code base is growing that much,
we're probably starting to hack.
We're using shortcuts,
we're using dirty tricks,
to just get things working,
which goes back to large,
which goes back to ugly.
This all has to stop.
So there is nothing that
we talk about in this video
that ever puts integrity as a cost.
Nothing trumps integrity.
We have to get serious about it.
As we talk and learn
about Go, you're gonna see
how the language puts integrity first.
Over and over and over again.
Now once we write a piece
of code that has integrity,
then we wanna make sure,
optimizing for correctness,
that that code is readable.
Now, what does readability mean?
It's another buzzword, and this can change
depending on the language
that we're dealing with.
All right, it means that we
have to structure our systems
to be more comprehensible,
readable, means reliability.
But for me, readability means two things.
It means that the average
developer on your team
should be able to read that piece of code
and have a good understanding
of what it's doing, logically.
And the second part,
which is really critical,
that the code that we write
does not hide its cost,
does hide the cost of its impact
on the program, and on the machine.
That, to me, is readability.
And we can do this in Go, again,
because we're writing
code for a real machine.
We can write code
that doesn't create
large abstraction layers
that hides the cost of what we're doing.
This is what I'm looking
for in readability.
Can the average developer
understand the logic,
and does this code hide cost?
Because if it hides cost, this
is gonna hurt us in the end.
Optimizing for correctness
means readability first.
And so Chuck Moore said this,
a well-designed language
has a one-to-one correlation
between its source code
and its object code.
It's obvious to the programmer
what the code will be
generated from their source.
He's basically saying that
a well-designed language
allows you to have
a mental model of what's
gonna happen on the machine.
It allows you to have
this idea of readability
where you can understand the choices
and the impacts of your choices.
You know, things like constructors
and operator overloading,
these are things that
hide the cost of code.
I could show you a piece
of code that, in C++,
that has constructors and destructors
and operator overloads and show
you some very simple calls.
And you will have no clue
what's going to happen,
especially between version
to version to version to C++.
And that's not readable code.
Go is not going to allow that.
You could somehow do it to yourself,
but I'm hopefully gonna show you,
not only why you don't wanna do this,
but you do this now for yourself.
Don't do this, let's go for readability.
Let's not hide the cost of the
decisions that we're making.
Now, the next thing is simplicity.
I've made it Number Three.
But simplicity is really interesting.
I want you to think about this.
Simplicity is about hiding complexity.
Now, think about this for one second.
If readability is about
not hiding the cost
of the code or the
decisions you're making,
right, the impact, that's readability.
Don't hide, right?
And then simplicity
comes in and says, whoa.
Let's hide complexity.
When you really think about it,
readability and simplicity
are fighting with each other,
aren't they, they're on
opposite sides of this dynamic.
Yet we put them together all the time.
And this is what makes simplicity
so special when it's done.
This idea that you hide complexity
without losing your ability to understand
the cost of your decisions.
Go does this all the time.
Go is so amazing, it's
garbage-collector hides
the complexity of memory management.
Yet, we're gonna be able to know
the choices that we make,
what effect we're having on the heap.
See that, see what I'm saying here?
Hiding, you know, we hate
complexity, simplicity?
But we didn't hide the
cost of our decisions.
This is going to happen
over and over again in Go.
So simplicity is not something
you can get to day one.
Readability, optimizing
for correctness, yes.
Simplicity is something
that comes over time,
it comes with refactoring,
it comes with our ability
to prototype, to learn, to understand,
and come back and hide
complexity over time.
And so it's something
that we should strive for,
it's something that we wanna get to.
But it's not something that
we can really do day one.
Now, the very last thing is performance.
And I put it last because there are times
when performance is going
to be your highest priority.
You're going to write a piece of code,
and it's not gonna be fast enough.
This is going to happen.
And now, we have to make
a conscious decision.
We're gonna walk away from simplicity,
we're gonna walk away from readability.
We can never walk away from integrity.
But now we might write a
piece of code that is clever,
that is a little complex.
But, we have to make sure
that we're doing this
based on measured results.
We can never guess about performance.
Our measurements must be relevant.
We must profile to decide that
something isn't fast enough.
In lessons, as we go on,
I'm gonna show you how to do this.
I'm gonna show you what happens
when you guess or assume
about performance.
Performance is not, it's
about not wasting effort.
Not your effort, not
an algorithm's effort.
Okay, it's about being
mechanically sympathetic.
Mechanical sympathy means that
if performance matters, then,
how code runs on the machine must matter,
because as we already
said, it is the machine
that will dictate how the
performance of our software goes.
We can fight the machine.
I don't care what language
you're using at that point.
You're not gonna see the performance.
Or we can be sympathetic with the machine.
Go allows us to be sympathetic.
In fact, you don't even realize it,
but if you follow just even
some of the language idioms,
they're pushing you towards
mechanical sympathy.
They're pushing you in
the right direction.
Nothing in Go is magic.
It's just good, sound,
engineering principles.
It's good design and philosophy
that when we follow, we
get to take advantage of.
So that's it for preparing our minds.
Everything that I do, moving forward,
is gonna be built around integrity,
readability, simplicity,
and then performance.
It's gonna be built around
optimizing for correctness.
It's gonna be built around productivity.
These are the things that matter.
These are the things
that must matter to us.
And I want to show you,
not tell you,
I wanna show you so you
do this for yourself,
how special this language is
when it comes to these things.